<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Public Health | Meethila Gade</title>
    <link>https://brain-discourse.github.io/tag/public-health/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://brain-discourse.github.io/tag/public-health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Public Health</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://brain-discourse.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Public Health</title>
      <link>https://brain-discourse.github.io/tag/public-health/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Justifiable paternalism or justice</title>
      <link>https://brain-discourse.github.io/post/ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://brain-discourse.github.io/post/ethics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to not have a choice despite being able to make a “choice”? Do we as individuals reserve a right to develop and maintain self-destructive habits? Public health in today’s world is a double-edged sword, stakeholders may not always benefit but others may see a new ray of hope. A review of worker rights within the US illustrates the economic quasi-coercion [1] associated with capitalism while the tobacco industry gives us a glimpse of the omnipresent psychological manipulation people were regularly subjected to. These two issues illustrate the restrictions on an individual’s ability to choose freely and the application of paternalism through public health interventions (OSHA regulations and tobacco tax) to successfully tackle situations when that individual is unable to make an informed decision to avoid harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The industrialization and urbanization that followed the turn of the 20th century fuelled a precipitous rise in the number of factory jobs [2]. Yet job safety and worker welfare were of little concern in an era when profit was king. Worker safety was the responsibility of the workers themselves, as demonstrated by the  Lochner vs New York, 1905 [3] case, which favored the liberty of contract over the health of bakers laboring in unhealthy conditions. Corporations were virtually insulated from liability due to occupational hazards because sustained low-level exposures were easily deniable. They took too long to manifest and not many diseases could be linked to a person’s occupation due to lack of immediate evidence. Silicosis was often mistaken for tuberculosis and only after the Hawk’s Nest Tunnel Disaster[3] was silica exposure recognized as an occupational hazard. Due to the massive press coverage of the incident, factories releasing silica dust, for the first time worked towards reducing exposure levels. There was, however, no legal or regulatory authority to enforce corrective action and assess risk. The environmental movement and the civil rights movement in the 1960s created a climate of reform paving a way for the Occupational Safety and Health Act (OSHA) in 1970, during the Nixon era [3]. Under this act, employers were responsible for ensuring the safety of their employees and work safety laws were passed and enforced [3].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against this societal backdrop of gradually increasing attention to safety and health, advertising campaigns of the tobacco industry ensured a steady rise in cigarette consumption through psychological manipulation. Advertisers in the early 1900s bypassed consumers capacity to reason by active manipulation, rendering them confined to choose smartly. Marketing campaigns like “Reach for the Lucky instead of the Sweet” or “Doctors smoke Camels” walked the fine line so characteristic of the consumer culture between demanding conformity and asserting individuality [4]. This drastic rise in cigarette consumption was followed by an attendant rise in the incidence of lung cancers. Increasing interest in the relationship between smoking and lung carcinoma spurred the cigarette industry to launch a massive disinformation campaign by casting doubts on the science. Only after the release of the Surgeon General’s Report- “Smoking and Health” [5] in 1964 did the government decide to ban TV advertising of cigarettes and jumpstart the Non- Smoker’s Rights Movement [5]. The association between both, the industrial accidents and the rise in lung cancer incidents was the lack of causal relationship between exposure and the outcome, laying emphasis on the need for a precautionary approach [6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R.E Goodin states, “Harm is of such a nature that it could be avoided by affected if they so choose. The incurring of the harm requires the active cooperation of the victim” [7]. One can say that smokers bring harm to themselves by rationalizing their addiction, anchoring fallacy and time discounting [7] because of voluntary decisions made in the early years influenced by one’s culture, peer pressure, and perpetually rampant manipulation by the media. At the same time, an employee’s decision to take a certain level of risk in exchange for money and job security is his own choice, but is such a decision true consent? R.E. Goodin [7]sheds some light on this topic by stating that smokers are usually not giving their rightful consent when they develop the habit of smoking. He says people can be held to have consented only if they knew to what they were supposedly consenting. This habit is usually picked up during the teenage years when people are minors and, thus, ineligible to give their consent. The addictive nature of nicotine ensures that smoking will soon spiral into addiction. Addiction is the absence of free will [8] and, therefore, taking an addict’s consent would be tantamount to a first order violation. Similarly, a person agreeing to a hazardous job to not stay unemployed is also not giving rightful consent. These examples illustrate the concept of quasi- coercion [1], in which consent dictated by unfair restriction of alternatives is an indirect, pervasive erosion of choice. The quasi-coercive nature of smoking and unsafe employment are fundamentally due to social institutions. In this unfair market, the inequality between certain sections of the society grows over time, leaving them with no bargaining power, making risk taking a mandatory job requirement. Quasi- coercion, thus, creates only an illusion of autonomy [1].
Differential risk of disease in different socioeconomic classes is also evident. The impact of widespread anti-smoking campaigns is clear among the educated and wealthy. However, the people with lower socioeconomic status due to lack awareness on health concerns of cigarettes and occupational stress, resort to smoking as a coping mechanism. As a result, they become victims of the regressive cigarette tax and denormalization of smoking and are subject to increasing marginalization and stigmatization. This demographic is also more susceptible to economic quasi-coercion. Daniel M Gade [9] very effectively highlights this issue by asking what would happen if every individual had a chance to start equal? Inequalities in health status are not solely the consequences of inequality in health services, but also a result of lifestyle choices one makes due to inequity. This emphasizes the need for equitable redistribution of social goods since having equality in health care does not compensate us for the unequal risks of getting ill. Guaranteeing equal opportunity necessitates the elimination of differential risk, the prevention of excess illness, and the alteration of fundamental institutional arrangements [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring equal opportunity would require the elimination of harmful choices. Does the government have the right of stopping people who want to live and act in a way they falsely believe to be safe? Is it the responsibility of public health workers to ensure that consent to smoke or take up risk is rightfully taken and by no means coerced on an individual?  The ultimate justification for paternalism must be utilitarian, ensuring that overall social utility is maximized when utilities of all members of the society are maximized [7]. Decisions regarded as self-destructive and unhealthy are not conclusive grounds for interventions. Only if these decisions are a result of independently defined failures of competency such as addiction or low socio-economic status is paternalistic intervention justified. Yet unhealthy lifestyles impose a substantial burden on an uninvolved portion of society that, nevertheless, must share the costs of illnesses created by said choices. In response to this, we follow John Stuart Mills’s Harm principle [10] and work our way towards Neoprohibitionism [8] by changing norms (ban on smoking in public places) and making each pack of cigarettes reflect the price of the negative externalities (cigarette tax).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In argument, one may bring up the issue of autonomy and individual liberty of smokers and workers, which conflicts with public health interventions. There exists a conflict between liberty and equality, such that unduly paternalistic and stringent regulations prize workers’ health more highly than the workers themselves[1]. Several professions such as that of a soldier, stuntman, and firefighter involve risks, yet are regularly portrayed as heroic; why should exposure risk be classified differently. Doesn’t this overreaching by the meddlesome nanny state agency (OSHA) violate the concept of autonomy? A smoker’s opinion is lost in the tyranny of the majority. The rights of the individual are subsumed within the social contract [7] which permits government intervention in situations in which individual competence to make rational decisions is temporarily or permanently undermined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the lessons of history, while, it may take a tragedy to realize the importance of safety and health regulations, one can successfully counter such issues with appropriate measures and support from the industry and the government in the form of OSHA compliance and introduction of cigarette taxes. A paternalistic approach may seem slightly overbearing, but it is necessary to ensure social equity and protect the vulnerable from exploitation. Although autonomy or personal freedom is central to human rights [11], this autonomy can at times be illusionary with regard to “valid consent”. Successful public health interventions in the field of occupational health and tobacco industry demonstrate that “harm” despite being instilled upon oneself as a “choice” is nothing but an illusion of autonomy, differentially distributed in our society. It is, therefore, the duty of public health professionals to ameliorate injustice and establish trust in people by providing them with adequate information, thereby, allowing them to make informed decisions. After all, an intervention is only effective when there is a significant amount of public trust involved in adapting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REFERENCES&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniels, N. (1985). Doth OSHA protect too much? Just Health Care,140-179. doi:10.1017/cbo9780511624971.008&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colgrove, J. (2018, September 03). History Session #1. The Origins of Public Health. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colgrove, J. (2018, September 18). History Session #5. Your Job May Be Hazardous to Your Health: The History of Occupational Illness. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brandt, A. (2007). Cigarette Century: The Rise, Fall and Deadly Persistence of the Product that Defined America. Tobacco Control,16(5), 69-101. doi:10.1136/tc.2007.021311&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Colgrove, J. (2018, September 20). History Session #6. Tobacco and the Dilemma of Chronic Disease. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer, R. (2018, September 03). Ethics Session #1. From Bioethics to an Ethics of Public Health: The Priority of Population Well-Being. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goodin, R. E. (1989). No smoking: The ethical issues. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer, R. (2018, September 18). Ethics Session #5. Engineering Mass Behavioral Change: The Case of Tobacco Control. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer, R. (2018, September 20). Ethics Session #6. Justice, the Duty to Protect, and the Duty to Provide: Securing Occupational Safety and Addressing the Inequalities in US Health Care. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bayer, R. (2018, September 4). Ethics Session #2. John Stuart Mill, Liberty, and Public health: Limiting state intervention. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedman, L. (2018, September 03). Human Rights Session #1. Introduction to Human Rights and Its Relationship to Public Health. Lecture presented at MPH Core, Mailman School of Public Health, Columbia University in USA, New York.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The blue pills that became NYC’s worst nightmare</title>
      <link>https://brain-discourse.github.io/post/oped/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://brain-discourse.github.io/post/oped/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2017, roughly 64,000 people died from a drug overdose in the United States - the largest
annual increase in drug-related deaths ever recorded by the CDC in history. New York City
lost 1,374 people, with Staten Island being the epicenter of the overdose epidemic where 101
residents succumbed to drug overdoses, mostly involving opioids in 2017
alone. Infamously called painkiller paradise, this borough, a 30-minute ferry ride away from
Manhattan is replete with blue OxyContin pills and adorned with used heroin needles. This
is a public health crisis transcending age, race, and income.  
What started out as a war on drugs during the Nixon era to stigmatize the people of color
became a national epidemic, yet our response has long been rooted in racism and
elitism. With whites being called victims and blacks referred to as addicts, we see a huge
divide based on America’s social hierarchies. It is not as if the addicts have made a choice to
succumb to drugs at the cost of their job, their family or loved ones but are simply the victims
of quasi - coercion due to the addictive nature of the problem. We have little compunction in
saying that the addict&amp;rsquo;s free will is sufficiently impaired, that his apparent consent counts for
naught, emphasizing the need to tackle this problem more like a medical challenge than
criminal justice by embracing compassion and evidence-based interventions,
especially among the marginalized.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prevalent definition of addiction–a destructive and compulsive behavioral trait marked
by moral failure needs to be supplanted by the one which describes it as a physical
dependence, something which can be treated as a medical condition. Medication-assisted
treatments (MAT), mostly using Methadone and Suboxone to aid addicts with symptoms of
withdrawal like nausea, body ache, anxiety, excessive sweating, and hallucinations are a need
of the hour. Supplemented with psychotherapy and clean supply of prescription heroin it
can successfully bring down the dependency of people on opioids by addressing behavioral
issues, supporting recovery and preventing relapse. With Methadone and Suboxone being
opioids themselves, this intervention fulfills the opioid craving and stops the cycle; however,
it is not meant to be used as a replacement but to bring drug-use to a safer habit with a
consistent dosage pattern. This strategy is both effective and significantly cheaper than
adding inpatient beds at rehabilitation centers. However, only about one-third of addiction
programs in America offer this treatment, with women, Blacks and Hispanics being less
likely to receive it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the New York City health department has implemented various interventions to
address the medical, psychological and socio-cultural aspects of the epidemic
such as MAT, increased insurance coverage, psychotherapy, good Samaritan laws, and
substance use counseling, they have failed to reach the marginalized sections of the society.
Despite the Healing NYC plan proposed last year to bring down opioid-related deaths to less
than 35%, the epidemic continues to break up families and is one of the leading causes of
higher crime rates and deaths, predominantly in Staten Island and South Bronx, the two
boroughs with many marginalized communities. With overdoses increasing to
112% among black New Yorkers, it is agonizing for people of color to see no commensurate
regard for vulnerable communities who continue to be criminalized and written off, demanding a bipartisan response. It means replacing addiction with physical dependence,
reducing the stigma surrounding the issue and encouraging doctors to provide medication for
addiction in a primary care setting. To make these drugs more accessible to
the marginalized, effort should be made to reduce the high copayments for these drugs and
reach out to communities where issues like these are more prevalent instead of just branding
them as addicts.
  
  These interventions don&amp;rsquo;t seem to be exempt from the argument that some patients will
continue to misuse opioids and spiral down to abuse. However, the model has been
successfully implemented in places like Sydney, Lisbon, and Vancouver, and
has strategically brought down overdose rates. Portugal single-handedly transitioned from the
“heroin capital” of the world to a country with the lowest drug-related death rate in Western
Europe in the past decade by adopting the harm reduction approach. Portugal’s story
reiterates the need for working towards addiction and addiction therapy as a medical
condition, not a moral failure and making maintenance drugs almost as accessible as other
forms of medication. Effort should be made to decriminalize drug use, eliminate the stigma
and reluctance in seeking help, especially among the marginalized. While we can’t
completely eradicate opioids, it is possible to save numerous lives if we treat them as sick
humans who need helping hands, not handcuffs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
